Guide to the Russell G. (R. G.) Vliet Papers
The Wittliff Collections
- Works
  - Subject Files, undated
    - Projects (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Reptiles/dinosaur tracks (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Sky and weather (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Texas clippings (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - Texas folklore photocopies (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - Trees (Box 32, Folder 6)
- Personal Papers, circa 1930-1990
  Scope and Contents
  Personal Papers are arranged into the following sub-series: Correspondence, Photographs, Scrapbooks, Clippings, Notebooks, Medical Records, Legal Records, Financial Records, Computer Disks, and Artifacts.
  - Business Correspondence, 1955-1984
    Business correspondence relates to Vliet's writing career, and covers such subjects as writing submissions, editing of works to be published, royalties for published works. Correspondents include various poetry and literary journals, Texas Institute of Letters, the Ford Foundation, and Vliet's agent, Lucy Kroll, of the Lucy Kroll Agency.
    Two non-correspondence files were filed by the author with this business correspondence, and are located at the beginning of this group of correspondence. The first of these, "Market List", is a list of journals and publishers to contact; the second file, "Notes on copyright", includes lists of Vliet's works and their copyright status (transfer of copyright, renewal dates for copyright, etc.) and notes regarding royalties.
    - Market list, undated (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - Notes on copyright, undated (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - Accent, 1956-1958 (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - AGNI Review, 1981-1983 (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - Beloit Poetry Journal, 1957-1965 (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - Bodley Head, 1967 (Box 32, Folder 12)
    - Black Warrior Review, 1981 (Box 32, Folder 13)
    - Dubus, Andres, 1983 (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - Ford Foundation, 1959-1960 (Box 32, Folder 15)
    - Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1975-1978 (Box 32, Folder 16)
    - Houston Public Library (n.d, exhibit materials), undated (Box 32, Folder 17)
    - Hudson Review, 1961-1980 (Box 32, Folder 18)
    - Kayak, 1964-1969 (Box 32, Folder 19)
    - Lucy Kroll Agency, 1961-1984 (Box 32, Folder 20)
    - PN Review, 1982 (Box 32, Folder 21)
    - Poetry, 1979 (Box 32, Folder 22)
    - Poetry Center, 1966 (Box 32, Folder 23)
    - Poetry Now, 1979 (Box 32, Folder 24)
    - Pressworks Publishing, Inc., 1983 (Box 32, Folder 25)
    - Quarterly Review of Literature (Bard College), 1960-1961 (Box 32, Folder 26)
    - Random House (Rob Cowley), 1980-1985 (Box 32, Folder 27)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1967 (Box 32, Folder 28)
    - San Francisco Review, 1960-1962 (Box 32, Folder 29)
    - Saturday Review, 1957 (Box 32, Folder 30)
    - Shearer Publishing, 1982-1984 (Box 32, Folder 31)
    - Southwest Review, 1956-1982 (Box 32, Folder 32)
    - Southwest Texas State University, 1960-1983 (Box 32, Folder 33)
    - Texas Institute of Letters (including Paisano fellowship notes, application), 1967-1983 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Texas Observer, 1980 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Texas Quarterly (University of Texas), 1963 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - University of Texas, 1982 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - University Theatre (University of Nebraska), 1959 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Wisconsin Players (University of Wisconsin), 1956 (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - Vermont Council on the Arts, 1978 (Box 33, Folder 7)
    - Views (University of Louisville, 1960 (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - Viking Press (Malcom Cowley), 1965-1983 (Box 33, Folder 9)
    - Whitehead and Whitehead, undated (Box 33, Folder 10)
    - Other business correspondents A-Z, unidentified, 1955-1983 (Box 33, Folder 11)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1958-1985
    Personal correspondence in this subseries includes letters to Vliet from long-time friends such as Ruth Bloom, Harry Clauss, Alan Distler, John Haag, Ralph Houston, and David Lyttle. Several letters from Vliet to Ralph Houston are also included here, presumably sent to Ann Vliet after R.G. Vliet's death. These letters are of special interest in that they discuss Vliet's writing and his health. Correspondence from Vliet's family include genealogical information, and a letter from Vliet's father, R.G. Vliet, Sr., regarding the use of the name "R.G. Vliet" in published materials.
    - Barney, William D., 1982 (Box 33, Box 12)
    - Bloom, Ruth, 1965-1980 (Box 33, Box 13)
    - Brodile and Early Family (including genealogy); Letters from R.A. Trombley (Uncle Russ and Aunt Grace), undated (Box 33, Box 14)
    - Clauss, Harry and Rusty, 1960-1983 (Box 33, Box 15-16)
    - Distler, Alan, 1958-1969, undated (Box 34, Box 1)
    - Haag, John and Jan, 1966-1974 (Box 34, Box 2)
    - Houston, Ralph: Letters to Vliet, 1978-1984 (Box 34, Box 3)
    - Houston, Ralph: Letters from Vliet, 1961-1983 (Box 34, Box 4)
    - Houston, Ralph: Material collected by Houston on Vliet, undated (Box 34, Box 5)
    - Lyttle, David (including manuscript "Down Near the Back Road" and annotated book of poetry No Other Time), 1963-1985 (Box 34, Box 6)
    - Peebles, Ramona "Princess", 1981 (Box 34, Box 7)
    - Texas City High School, 1968 (Box 34, Box 8)
    - Southwest Texas State University (James Barton, Luann Brunson, Bob Hardesty), undated (Box 34, Box 9)
    - Vliet, R.G., Sr. (Vliet's father, re. use of Vliet name), undated (Box 34, Box 10)
    - Vliet, Brooke, 1980 (Box 34, Box 11)
    - Westerfield, Hargis, 1974-1977 (Box 34, Box 12)
    - Whitworth, Mr. and Mrs. (from Vliet), 1964 (Box 34, Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous personal correspondence, 1981-1985 (Box 35, Box 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1900-1980
    Photographs in this subseries are divided into the following groups: photographs of R.G. Vliet alone, Vliet and his immediate family, Vliet and extended family, Mexico snapshots, friends, workspaces, and pets. Most are color snapshots from Vliet's personal life, most are not labeled with identifying information. See also Subseries C: Scrapbook, for additional photographs, especially from Vliet's youth.
    - Vliet, R.G. (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Vliet, R.G., Ann, Brooke, and other family snapshots (Box 35, Folder 3-4)
    - Vliet, R.G. – parents, grandparents, and other family (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Mexico snapshots (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - Friends and other unidentified snapshots (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Workspaces and desks (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - Animals and pets (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook, 1930-1980
    This scrapbook serves as Vliet's baby book, and documents his activities as a Boy Scout and Eagle Scout, his high school days (including his diploma), and college days at Southwest Texas State University, as well as some examples of his early poetry and sketches. Formats include photographs, drawings, newsclippings, pressed flowers, awards and badges, membership cards, letters, drafts of poetry.
  - Clippings, undated (Box 36, Folder 1)
    Clippings in this subseries cover subjects ranging from Vliet's early play productions to the posthumous publication of his last novel, Scorpio Rising. These clippings were maintained by the author and filed along with play programs for several plays. This original order has been maintained, so that clippings regarding specific plays are filed here along with the play programs.
  - Notebooks, 1955, undated
    This subseries is comprised of Vliet's handwritten notes for a class taken at Yale School of Drama, "History of the Theater", in 1955.
    - Yale School of Drama, "History of the Theater", 1955 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Personal Phone Book (Box 36, Folder 2a)
  - Medical Records, 1982-1989
    Records in this subseries include correspondence, photocopied clippings, and doctors' reports regarding R. G. Vliet's fight against lymphoma from 1982 until his death in 1984. Also included are records relating to Ann Vliet's health from to 1987-1989.
    - Vliet, R. G., 1982-1984 (Box 36, Folder 3-4)
    - Vliet, Ann, 1987-1989 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Legal Records, undated
    R.G. Vliet's Last Will and Testament (1983) is included in this subseries, along with documents relating to a 1983 purchase of land in Kyle, Texas, and Ann Vliet's 1985-86 retirement and move to Kyle.
    - Last Will and Testament of R. G. Vliet (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - R. G. Vliet's driver's license, State of Massachusetts and International Certificate of Vaccination, undated (Box 36, Folder 6a)
    - Ann Vliet's retirement and real estate documents, undated (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - Financial Records, 1964-1990
    Check registers, bank statements, tax receipts and notes comprise one-half of this subseries. The second half includes financial notes and notebooks maintained by R. G. Vliet, which document expenditures relating to research and writing and may have been tax deductible.
    - Check Registers, 1964-1974 (Box 36, Folder 8-9)
    - Check Registers, 1975-1985 (Box 37, Folder 1-2)
    - Bank Statements, 1986-1987 (Box 37, Folder 3-6)
    - Bank Statements, 1988-1990 (Box 38, Folder 1-5)
    - Tax Receipts and Notes, 1984 (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - Financial notes and notebooks, 1960-1980 (Box 39, Folder 1-6)
  - Computer Disks, undated (Box 40, Folder 1-4)
    Eighty-six 5 1/4" floppy computer disks (with no print-outs) are included in this subseries. Many are untitled or have fragments of labels.
  - Artifacts, 1982, undated
    One award (from Southwest Texas State University) and several items of clothing, as well as Vliet's eyeglasses and case, are included in this subseries. The embroidered white cotton shirt worn by Vliet at his daughter's wedding (see Series 2: Personal, Subseries B: Photographs) can also be found here.
    - Southwest Texas State University Alumni Association Award for Distinguished Alumnus, 1982 (Box 41)
    - Denim hat (Box 42)
    - Embroidered white cotton shirt (Box 43)
    - Eyeglasses and case (Box 43)
    - One 12"x13" scrapbook containing newsclippings, photographs, and other ephemera, undated (Box 44)
    - Audiotape and LP recordings of 24 poems, by R.G. Vliet (Box 45)